1 Corinthians 14

1 Pursue the love, and seek earnestly the spiritual things, and rather that ye may prophecy,

2 for he who is speaking in an [unknown] tongue--to men he doth not speak, but to God, for no one doth hearken, and in spirit he doth speak secrets;

3 and he who is prophesying to men doth speak edification, and exhortation, and comfort;

4 he who is speaking in an [unknown] tongue, himself doth edify, and he who is prophesying, an assembly doth edify;

5 and I wish you all to speak with tongues, and more that ye may prophecy, for greater is he who is prophesying than he who is speaking with tongues, except one may interpret, that the assembly may receive edification.

6 And now, brethren, if I may come unto you speaking tongues, what shall I profit you, except I shall speak to you either in revelation, or in knowledge, or in prophesying, or in teaching?

7 yet the things without life giving sound--whether pipe or harp--if a difference in the sounds they may not give, how shall be known that which is piped or that which is harped?

8 for if also an uncertain sound a trumpet may give, who shall prepare himself for battle?

9 so also ye, if through the tongue, speech easily understood ye may not give-- how shall that which is spoken be known? for ye shall be speaking to air.

10 There are, it may be, so many kinds of voices in the world, and none of them is unmeaning,

11 if, then, I do not know the power of the voice, I shall be to him who is speaking a foreigner, and he who is speaking, is to me a foreigner;

12 so also ye, since ye are earnestly desirous of spiritual gifts, for the building up of the assembly seek that ye may abound;

13 wherefore he who is speaking in an [unknown] tongue--let him pray that he may interpret;

14 for if I pray in an [unknown] tongue, my spirit doth pray, and my understanding is unfruitful.

15 What then is it? I will pray with the spirit, and I will pray also with the understanding; I will sing psalms with the spirit, and I will sing psalms also with the understanding;

16 since, if thou mayest bless with the spirit, he who is filling the place of the unlearned, how shall he say the Amen at thy giving of thanks, since what thou dost say he hath not known?

17 for thou, indeed, dost give thanks well, but the other is not built up!

18 I give thanks to my God--more than you all with tongues speaking--

19 but in an assembly I wish to speak five words through my understanding, that others also I may instruct, rather than myriads of words in an [unknown] tongue.

20 Brethren, become not children in the understanding, but in the evil be ye babes, and in the understanding become ye perfect;

21 in the law it hath been written, that, `With other tongues and with other lips I will speak to this people, and not even so will they hear Me, saith the Lord;'

22 so that the tongues are for a sign, not to the believing, but to the unbelieving; and the prophesy [is] not for the unbelieving, but for the believing,

23 If, therefore, the whole assembly may come together, to the same place, and all may speak with tongues, and there may come in unlearned or unbelievers, will they not say that ye are mad?

24 and if all may prophecy, and any one may come in, an unbeliever or unlearned, he is convicted by all, he is discerned by all,

25 and so the secrets of his heart become manifest, and so having fallen upon [his] face, he will bow before God, declaring that God really is among you.

26 What then is it, brethren? whenever ye may come together, each of you hath a psalm, hath a teaching, hath a tongue, hath a revelation, hath an interpretation? let all things be for building up;

27 if an [unknown] tongue any one do speak, by two, or at the most, by three, and in turn, and let one interpret;

28 and if there may be no interpreter, let him be silent in an assembly, and to himself let him speak, and to God.

29 And prophets--let two or three speak, and let the others discern,

30 and if to another sitting [anything] may be revealed, let the first be silent;

31 for ye are able, one by one, all to prophesy, that all may learn, and all may be exhorted,

32 and the spiritual gift of prophets to prophets are subject,

33 for God is not [a God] of tumult, but of peace, as in all the assemblies of the saints.

34 Your women in the assemblies let them be silent, for it hath not been permitted to them to speak, but to be subject, as also the law saith;

35 and if they wish to learn anything, at home their own husbands let them question, for it is a shame to women to speak in an assembly.

36 From you did the word of God come forth? or to you alone did it come?

37 if any one doth think to be a prophet, or spiritual, let him acknowledge the things that I write to you--that of the Lord they are commands;

38 and if any one is ignorant--let him be ignorant;

39 so that, brethren, earnestly desire to prophesy, and to speak with tongues do not forbid;

40 let all things be done decently and in order.

1 Corinthians 16

1 And concerning the collection that [is] for the saints, as I directed to the assemblies of Galatia, so also ye--do ye;

2 on every first [day] of the week, let each one of you lay by him, treasuring up whatever he may have prospered, that when I may come then collections may not be made;

3 and whenever I may come, whomsoever ye may approve, through letters, these I will send to carry your favour to Jerusalem;

4 and if it be meet for me also to go, with me they shall go.

5 And I will come unto you, when I pass through Macedonia--for Macedonia I do pass through--

6 and with you, it may be, I will abide, or even winter, that ye may send me forward whithersoever I go,

7 for I do not wish to see you now in the passing, but I hope to remain a certain time with you, if the Lord may permit;

8 and I will remain in Ephesus till the Pentecost,

9 for a door to me hath been opened--great and effectual--and withstanders [are] many.

10 And if Timotheus may come, see that he may become without fear with you, for the work of the Lord he doth work, even as I,

11 no one, then, may despise him; and send ye him forward in peace, that he may come to me, for I expect him with the brethren;

12 and concerning Apollos our brother, much I did entreat him that he may come unto you with the brethren, and it was not at all [his] will that he may come now, and he will come when he may find convenient.

13 Watch ye, stand in the faith; be men, be strong;

14 let all your things be done in love.

15 And I entreat you, brethren, ye have known the household of Stephanas, that it is the first-fruit of Achaia, and to the ministration to the saints they did set themselves--

16 that ye also be subject to such, and to every one who is working with [us] and labouring;

17 and I rejoice over the presence of Stephanas, and Fortunatus, and Achaicus, because the lack of you did these fill up;

18 for they did refresh my spirit and yours; acknowledge ye, therefore, those who [are] such.

19 Salute you do the assemblies of Asia; salute you much in the Lord do Aquilas and Priscilla, with the assembly in their house;

20 salute you do all the brethren; salute ye one another in an holy kiss.

21 The salutation of [me] Paul with my hand;

22 if any one doth not love the Lord Jesus Christ--let him be anathema! The Lord hath come!

23 The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ [is] with you;

24 my love [is] with you all in Christ Jesus. Amen.

2 Corinthians 6

1 And working together also we call upon [you] that ye receive not in vain the grace of God--

2 for He saith, `In an acceptable time I did hear thee, and in a day of salvation I did help thee, lo, now [is] a well-accepted time; lo, now, a day of salvation,' --

3 in nothing giving any cause of offence, that the ministration may be not blamed,

4 but in everything recommending ourselves as God's ministrants; in much patience, in tribulations, in necessities, in distresses,

5 in stripes, in imprisonments, in insurrections, in labours, in watchings, in fastings,

6 in pureness, in knowledge, in long-suffering, in kindness, in the Holy Spirit, in love unfeigned,

7 in the word of truth, in the power of God, through the armour of the righteousness, on the right and on the left,

8 through glory and dishonour, through evil report and good report, as leading astray, and true;

9 as unknown, and recognized; as dying, and lo, we live; as chastened, and not put to death;

10 as sorrowful, and always rejoicing; as poor, and making many rich; as having nothing, and possessing all things.

11 Our mouth hath been open unto you, O Corinthians, our heart hath been enlarged!

12 ye are not straitened in us, and ye are straitened in your [own] bowels,

13 and [as] a recompense of the same kind, (as to children I say [it],) be ye enlarged--also ye!

14 Become not yoked with others--unbelievers, for what partaking [is there] to righteousness and lawlessness?

15 and what fellowship to light with darkness? and what concord to Christ with Belial? or what part to a believer with an unbeliever?

16 and what agreement to the sanctuary of God with idols? for ye are a sanctuary of the living God, according as God said--`I will dwell in them, and will walk among [them], and I will be their God, and they shall be My people,

17 wherefore, come ye forth out of the midst of them, and be separated, saith the Lord, and an unclean thing do not touch, and I--I will receive you,

18 and I will be to you for a Father, and ye--ye shall be to Me for sons and daughters, saith the Lord Almighty.'

2 Corinthians 11

1 O that ye were bearing with me a little of the folly, but ye also do bear with me:

2 for I am zealous for you with zeal of God, for I did betroth you to one husband, a pure virgin, to present to Christ,

3 and I fear, lest, as the serpent did beguile Eve in his subtilty, so your minds may be corrupted from the simplicity that [is] in the Christ;

4 for if, indeed, he who is coming doth preach another Jesus whom we did not preach, or another Spirit ye receive which ye did not receive, or other good news which ye did not accept--well were ye bearing [it],

5 for I reckon that I have been nothing behind the very chiefest apostles,

6 and even if unlearned in word--yet not in knowledge, but in every thing we were made manifest in all things to you.

7 The sin did I do--myself humbling that ye might be exalted, because freely the good news of God I did proclaim to you?

8 other assemblies I did rob, having taken wages, for your ministration;

9 and being present with you, and having been in want, I was chargeable to no one, for my lack did the brethren supply--having come from Macedonia--and in everything burdenless to you I did keep myself, and will keep.

10 The truth of Christ is in me, because this boasting shall not be stopped in regard to me in the regions of Achaia;

11 wherefore? because I do not love you? God hath known!

12 and what I do, I also will do, that I may cut off the occasion of those wishing an occasion, that in that which they boast they may be found according as we also;

13 for those such [are] false apostles, deceitful workers, transforming themselves into apostles of Christ,

14 and no wonder--for even the Adversary doth transform himself into a messenger of light;

15 no great thing, then, if also his ministrants do transform themselves as ministrants of righteousness--whose end shall be according to their works.

16 Again I say, may no one think me to be a fool; and if otherwise, even as a fool receive me, that I also a little may boast.

17 That which I speak, I speak not according to the Lord, but as in foolishness, in this the confidence of boasting;

18 since many boast according to the flesh, I also will boast:

19 for gladly do ye bear with the fools--being wise,

20 for ye bear, if any one is bringing you under bondage, if any one doth devour, if any one doth take away, if any one doth exalt himself, if any one on the face doth smite you;

21 in reference to dishonour I speak, how that we were weak, and in whatever any one is bold--in foolishness I say [it] --I also am bold.

22 Hebrews are they? I also! Israelites are they? I also! seed of Abraham are they? I also!

23 ministrants of Christ are they? --as beside myself I speak--I more; in labours more abundantly, in stripes above measure, in prisons more frequently, in deaths many times;

24 from Jews five times forty [stripes] save one I did receive;

25 thrice was I beaten with rods, once was I stoned, thrice was I shipwrecked, a night and a day in the deep I have passed;

26 journeyings many times, perils of rivers, perils of robbers, perils from kindred, perils from nations, perils in city, perils in wilderness, perils in sea, perils among false brethren;

27 in labouriousness and painfulness, in watchings many times, in hunger and thirst, in fastings many times, in cold and nakedness;

28 apart from the things without--the crowding upon me that is daily--the care of all the assemblies.

29 Who is infirm, and I am not infirm? who is stumbled, and I am not fired;

30 if to boast it behoveth [me], of the things of my infirmity I will boast;

31 the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ--who is blessed to the ages--hath known that I do not lie! --

32 In Damascus the ethnarch of Aretas the king was watching the city of the Damascenes, wishing to seize me,

33 and through a window in a rope basket I was let down, through the wall, and fled out of his hands.

2 Corinthians 12

1 To boast, really, is not profitable for me, for I will come to visions and revelations of the Lord.

2 I have known a man in Christ, fourteen years ago--whether in the body I have not known, whether out of the body I have not known, God hath known--such an one being caught away unto the third heaven;

3 and I have known such a man--whether in the body, whether out of the body, I have not known, God hath known, --

4 that he was caught away to the paradise, and heard unutterable sayings, that it is not possible for man to speak.

5 Of such an one I will boast, and of myself I will not boast, except in my infirmities,

6 for if I may wish to boast, I shall not be a fool, for truth I will say; but I forebear, lest any one in regard to me may think anything above what he doth see me, or doth hear anything of me;

7 and that by the exceeding greatness of the revelations I might not be exalted overmuch, there was given to me a thorn in the flesh, a messenger of the Adversary, that he might buffet me, that I might not be exalted overmuch.

8 Concerning this thing thrice the Lord did I call upon, that it might depart from me,

9 and He said to me, `Sufficient for thee is My grace, for My power in infirmity is perfected;' most gladly, therefore, will I rather boast in my infirmities, that the power of the Christ may rest on me:

10 wherefore I am well pleased in infirmities, in damages, in necessities, in persecutions, in distresses--for Christ; for whenever I am infirm, then I am powerful;

11 I have become a fool--boasting; ye--ye did compel me; for I ought by you to have been commended, for in nothing was I behind the very chiefest apostles--even if I am nothing.

12 The signs, indeed, of the apostle were wrought among you in all patience, in signs, and wonders, and mighty deeds,

13 for what is there in which ye were inferior to the rest of the assemblies, except that I myself was not a burden to you? forgive me this injustice!

14 Lo, a third time I am ready to come unto you, and I will not be a burden to you, for I seek not yours, but you, for the children ought not for the parents to lay up, but the parents for the children,

15 and I most gladly will spend and be entirely spent for your souls, even if, more abundantly loving you, less I am loved.

16 And be it [so], I--I did not burden you, but being crafty, with guile I did take you;

17 any one of those whom I have sent unto you--by him did I take advantage of you?

18 I entreated Titus, and did send with [him] the brother; did Titus take advantage of you? in the same spirit did we not walk? --did we not in the same steps?

19 Again, think ye that to you we are making defence? before God in Christ do we speak; and the all things, beloved, [are] for your up-building,

20 for I fear lest, having come, not such as I wish I may find you, and I--I may be found by you such as ye do not wish, lest there be strifes, envyings, wraths, revelries, evilspeakings, whisperings, puffings up, insurrections,

21 lest again having come, my God may humble me in regard to you, and I may bewail many of those having sinned before, and not having reformed concerning the uncleanness, and whoredom, and lasciviousness, that they did practise.

Galatians 1

1 Paul, an apostle--not from men, nor through man, but through Jesus Christ, and God the Father, who did raise him out of the dead--

2 and all the brethren with me, to the assemblies of Galatia:

3 Grace to you, and peace from God the Father, and our Lord Jesus Christ,

4 who did give himself for our sins, that he might deliver us out of the present evil age, according to the will of God even our Father,

5 to whom [is] the glory to the ages of the ages. Amen.

6 I wonder that ye are so quickly removed from Him who did call you in the grace of Christ to another good news;

7 that is not another, except there be certain who are troubling you, and wishing to pervert the good news of the Christ;

8 but even if we or a messenger out of heaven may proclaim good news to you different from what we did proclaim to you--anathema let him be!

9 as we have said before, and now say again, If any one to you may proclaim good news different from what ye did receive--anathema let him be!

10 for now men do I persuade, or God? or do I seek to please men? for if yet men I did please--Christ's servant I should not be.

11 And I make known to you, brethren, the good news that were proclaimed by me, that it is not according to man,

12 for neither did I from man receive it, nor was I taught [it], but through a revelation of Jesus Christ,

13 for ye did hear of my behaviour once in Judaism, that exceedingly I was persecuting the assembly of God, and wasting it,

14 and I was advancing in Judaism above many equals in age in mine own race, being more abundantly zealous of my fathers' deliverances,

15 and when God was well pleased--having separated me from the womb of my mother, and having called [me] through His grace--

16 to reveal His Son in me, that I might proclaim him good news among the nations, immediately I conferred not with flesh and blood,

17 nor did I go up to Jerusalem unto those who were apostles before me, but I went away to Arabia, and again returned to Damascus,

18 then, after three years I went up to Jerusalem to enquire about Peter, and remained with him fifteen days,

19 and other of the apostles I did not see, except James, the brother of the Lord.

20 And the things that I write to you, lo, before God--I lie not;

21 then I came to the regions of Syria and of Cilicia,

22 and was unknown by face to the assemblies of Judea, that [are] in Christ,

23 and only they were hearing, that `he who is persecuting us then, doth now proclaim good news--the faith that then he was wasting;'

24 and they were glorifying God in me.

Galatians 3

1 O thoughtless Galatians, who did bewitch you, not to obey the truth--before whose eyes Jesus Christ was described before among you crucified?

2 this only do I wish to learn from you--by works of law the Spirit did ye receive, or by the hearing of faith?

3 so thoughtless are ye! having begun in the Spirit, now in the flesh do ye end?

4 so many things did ye suffer in vain! if, indeed, even in vain.

5 He, therefore, who is supplying to you the Spirit, and working mighty acts among you--by works of law or by the hearing of faith [is it]?

6 according as Abraham did believe God, and it was reckoned to him--to righteousness;

7 know ye, then, that those of faith--these are sons of Abraham,

8 and the Writing having foreseen that by faith God doth declare righteous the nations did proclaim before the good news to Abraham--

9 `Blessed in thee shall be all the nations;' so that those of faith are blessed with the faithful Abraham,

10 for as many as are of works of law are under a curse, for it hath been written, `Cursed [is] every one who is not remaining in all things that have been written in the Book of the Law--to do them,'

11 and that in law no one is declared righteous with God, is evident, because `The righteous by faith shall live;'

12 and the law is not by faith, but--`The man who did them shall live in them.'

13 Christ did redeem us from the curse of the law, having become for us a curse, for it hath been written, `Cursed is every one who is hanging on a tree,'

14 that to the nations the blessing of Abraham may come in Christ Jesus, that the promise of the Spirit we may receive through the faith.

15 Brethren, as a man I say [it], even of man a confirmed covenant no one doth make void or doth add to,

16 and to Abraham were the promises spoken, and to his seed; He doth not say, `And to seeds,' as of many, but as of one, `And to thy seed,' which is Christ;

17 and this I say, A covenant confirmed before by God to Christ, the law, that came four hundred and thirty years after, doth not set aside, to make void the promise,

18 for if by law [be] the inheritance, [it is] no more by promise, but to Abraham through promise did God grant [it].

19 Why, then, the law? on account of the transgressions it was added, till the seed might come to which the promise hath been made, having been set in order through messengers in the hand of a mediator--

20 and the mediator is not of one, and God is one--

21 the law, then, [is] against the promises of God? --let it not be! for if a law was given that was able to make alive, truly by law there would have been the righteousness,

22 but the Writing did shut up the whole under sin, that the promise by faith of Jesus Christ may be given to those believing.

23 And before the coming of the faith, under law we were being kept, shut up to the faith about to be revealed,

24 so that the law became our child-conductor--to Christ, that by faith we may be declared righteous,

25 and the faith having come, no more under a child-conductor are we,

26 for ye are all sons of God through the faith in Christ Jesus,

27 for as many as to Christ were baptized did put on Christ;

28 there is not here Jew or Greek, there is not here servant nor freeman, there is not here male and female, for all ye are one in Christ Jesus;

29 and if ye [are] of Christ then of Abraham ye are seed, and according to promise-- heirs.

Galatians 5

1 In the freedom, then, with which Christ did make you free--stand ye, and be not held fast again by a yoke of servitude;

2 lo, I Paul do say to you, that if ye be circumcised, Christ shall profit you nothing;

3 and I testify again to every man circumcised, that he is a debtor to do the whole law;

4 ye were freed from the Christ, ye who in law are declared righteous; from the grace ye fell away;

5 for we by the Spirit, by faith, a hope of righteousness do wait for,

6 for in Christ Jesus neither circumcision availeth anything, nor uncircumcision, but faith through love working.

7 Ye were running well; who did hinder you--not to obey the truth?

8 the obedience [is] not of him who is calling you!

9 a little leaven the whole lump doth leaven;

10 I have confidence in regard to you in the Lord, that ye will be none otherwise minded; and he who is troubling you shall bear the judgment, whoever he may be.

11 And I, brethren, if uncircumcision I yet preach, why yet am I persecuted? then hath the stumbling-block of the cross been done away;

12 O that even they would cut themselves off who are unsettling you!

13 For ye--to freedom ye were called, brethren, only not the freedom for an occasion to the flesh, but through the love serve ye one another,

14 for all the law in one word is fulfilled--in this: `Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself;'

15 and if one another ye do bite and devour, see--that ye may not by one another be consumed.

16 And I say: In the Spirit walk ye, and the desire of the flesh ye may not complete;

17 for the flesh doth desire contrary to the Spirit, and the Spirit contrary to the flesh, and these are opposed one to another, that the things that ye may will--these ye may not do;

18 and if by the Spirit ye are led, ye are not under law.

19 And manifest also are the works of the flesh, which are: Adultery, whoredom, uncleanness, lasciviousness,

20 idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, strifes, emulations, wraths, rivalries, dissensions, sects,

21 envyings, murders, drunkennesses, revellings, and such like, of which I tell you before, as I also said before, that those doing such things the reign of God shall not inherit.

22 And the fruit of the Spirit is: Love, joy, peace, long-suffering, kindness, goodness, faith,

23 meekness, temperance: against such there is no law;

24 and those who are Christ's, the flesh did crucify with the affections, and the desires;

25 if we may live in the Spirit, in the Spirit also we may walk;

26 let us not become vain-glorious--one another provoking, one another envying!

Galatians 6

1 Brethren, if a man also may be overtaken in any trespass, ye who [are] spiritual restore such a one in a spirit of meekness, considering thyself--lest thou also may be tempted;

2 of one another the burdens bear ye, and so fill up the law of the Christ,

3 for if any one doth think [himself] to be something--being nothing--himself he doth deceive;

4 and his own work let each one prove, and then in regard to himself alone the glorying he shall have, and not in regard to the other,

5 for each one his own burden shall bear.

6 And let him who is instructed in the word share with him who is instructing--in all good things.

7 Be not led astray; God is not mocked; for what a man may sow--that also he shall reap,

8 because he who is sowing to his own flesh, of the flesh shall reap corruption; and he who is sowing to the Spirit, of the Spirit shall reap life age-during;

9 and in the doing good we may not be faint-hearted, for at the proper time we shall reap--not desponding;

10 therefore, then, as we have opportunity, may we work the good to all, and especially unto those of the household of the faith.

11 Ye see in how large letters I have written to you with my own hand;

12 as many as are willing to make a good appearance in the flesh, these constrain you to be circumcised--only that for the cross of the Christ they may not be persecuted,

13 for neither do those circumcised themselves keep the law, but they wish you to be circumcised, that in your flesh they may glory.

14 And for me, let it not be--to glory, except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through which to me the world hath been crucified, and I to the world;

15 for in Christ Jesus neither circumcision availeth anything, nor uncircumcision, but a new creation;

16 and as many as by this rule do walk--peace upon them, and kindness, and on the Israel of God!

17 Henceforth, let no one give me trouble, for I the scars of the Lord Jesus in my body do bear.

18 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [is] with your spirit, brethren! Amen.

Ephesians 6

1 The children! obey your parents in the Lord, for this is righteous;

2 honour thy father and mother,

3 which is the first command with a promise, `That it may be well with thee, and thou mayest live a long time upon the land.'

4 And the fathers! provoke not your children, but nourish them in the instruction and admonition of the Lord.

5 The servants! obey the masters according to the flesh with fear and trembling, in the simplicity of your heart, as to the Christ;

6 not with eye-service as men-pleasers, but as servants of the Christ, doing the will of God out of soul,

7 with good-will serving, as to the Lord, and not to men,

8 having known that whatever good thing each one may do, this he shall receive from the Lord, whether servant or freeman.

9 And the masters! the same things do ye unto them, letting threatening alone, having known that also your Master is in the heavens, and acceptance of persons is not with him.

10 As to the rest, my brethren, be strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might;

11 put on the whole armour of God, for your being able to stand against the wiles of the devil,

12 because we have not the wrestling with blood and flesh, but with the principalities, with the authorities, with the world-rulers of the darkness of this age, with the spiritual things of the evil in the heavenly places;

13 because of this take ye up the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to resist in the day of the evil, and all things having done--to stand.

14 Stand, therefore, having your loins girt about in truth, and having put on the breastplate of the righteousness,

15 and having the feet shod in the preparation of the good-news of the peace;

16 above all, having taken up the shield of the faith, in which ye shall be able all the fiery darts of the evil one to quench,

17 and the helmet of the salvation receive, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the saying of God,

18 through all prayer and supplication praying at all times in the Spirit, and in regard to this same, watching in all perseverance and supplication for all the saints--

19 and in behalf of me, that to me may be given a word in the opening of my mouth, in freedom, to make known the secret of the good news,

20 for which I am an ambassador in a chain, that in it I may speak freely--as it behoveth me to speak.

21 And that ye may know--ye also--the things concerning me--what I do, all things make known to you shall Tychicus, the beloved brother and faithful ministrant in the Lord,

22 whom I did send unto you for this very thing, that ye might know the things concerning us, and that he might comfort your hearts.

23 Peace to the brethren, and love, with faith, from God the Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ!

24 The grace with all those loving our Lord Jesus Christ--undecayingly! Amen.

Philippians 3

1 As to the rest, my brethren, rejoice in the Lord; the same things to write to you to me indeed is not tiresome, and for you [is] sure;

2 look to the dogs, look to the evil-workers, look to the concision;

3 for we are the circumcision, who by the Spirit are serving God, and glorying in Christ Jesus, and in flesh having no trust,

4 though I also have [cause of] trust in flesh. If any other one doth think to have trust in flesh, I more;

5 circumcision on the eighth day! of the race of Israel! of the tribe of Benjamin! a Hebrew of Hebrews! according to law a Pharisee!

6 according to zeal persecuting the assembly! according to righteousness that is in law becoming blameless!

7 But what things were to me gains, these I have counted, because of the Christ, loss;

8 yes, indeed, and I count all things to be loss, because of the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord, because of whom of the all things I suffered loss, and do count them to be refuse, that Christ I may gain, and be found inhim,

9 not having my righteousness, which [is] of law, but that which [is] through faith of Christ--the righteousness that is of God by the faith,

10 to know him, and the power of his rising again, and the fellowship of his sufferings, being conformed to his death,

11 if anyhow I may attain to the rising again of the dead.

12 Not that I did already obtain, or have been already perfected; but I pursue, if also I may lay hold of that for which also I was laid hold of by the Christ Jesus;

13 brethren, I do not reckon myself to have laid hold; and one thing--the things behind indeed forgetting, and to the things before stretching forth--

14 to the mark I pursue for the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.

15 As many, therefore, as [are] perfect--let us think this, and if [in] anything ye think otherwise, this also shall God reveal to you,

16 but to what we have come--by the same rule walk, the same thing think;

17 become followers together of me, brethren, and observe those thus walking, according as ye have us--a pattern;

18 for many walk of whom many times I told you--and now also weeping tell--the enemies of the cross of the Christ!

19 whose end [is] destruction, whose god [is] the belly, and whose glory [is] in their shame, who the things on earth are minding.

20 For our citizenship is in the heavens, whence also a Saviour we await--the Lord Jesus Christ--

21 who shall transform the body of our humiliation to its becoming conformed to the body of his glory, according to the working of his power, even to subject to himself the all things.

Philippians 4

1 So then, my brethren, beloved and longed for, my joy and crown, so stand ye in the Lord, beloved.

2 Euodia I exhort, and Syntyche I exhort, to be of the same mind in the Lord;

3 and I ask also thee, genuine yoke-fellow, be assisting those women who in the good news did strive along with me, with Clement also, and the others, my fellow-workers, whose names [are] in the book of life.

4 Rejoice in the Lord always; again I will say, rejoice;

5 let your forbearance be known to all men; the Lord [is] near;

6 for nothing be anxious, but in everything by prayer, and by supplication, with thanksgiving, let your requests be made known unto God;

7 and the peace of God, that is surpassing all understanding, shall guard your hearts and your thoughts in Christ Jesus.

8 As to the rest, brethren, as many things as are true, as many as [are] grave, as many as [are] righteous, as many as [are] pure, as many as [are] lovely, as many as [are] of good report, if any worthiness, and if any praise, these things think upon;

9 the things that also ye did learn, and receive, and hear, and saw in me, those do, and the God of the peace shall be with you.

10 And I rejoiced in the Lord greatly, that now at length ye flourished again in caring for me, for which also ye were caring, and lacked opportunity;

11 not that in respect of want I say [it], for I did learn in the things in which I am--to be content;

12 I have known both to be abased, and I have known to abound; in everything and in all things I have been initiated, both to be full and to be hungry, both to abound and to be in want.

13 For all things I have strength, in Christ's strengthening me;

14 but ye did well, having communicated with my tribulation;

15 and ye have known, even ye Philippians, that in the beginning of the good news when I went forth from Macedonia, no assembly did communicate with me in regard to giving and receiving except ye only;

16 because also in Thessalonica, both once and again to my need ye sent;

17 not that I seek after the gift, but I seek after the fruit that is overflowing to your account;

18 and I have all things, and abound; I am filled, having received from Epaphroditus the things from you--an odour of a sweet smell--a sacrifice acceptable, well-pleasing to God:

19 and my God shall supply all your need, according to His riches in glory in Christ Jesus;

20 and to God, even our Father, [is] the glory--to the ages of the ages. Amen.

21 Salute ye every saint in Christ Jesus; there salute you the brethren with me;

22 there salute you all the saints, and specially those of Caesar's house;

23 the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [is] with you all. Amen.

Colossians 3

1 If, then, ye were raised with the Christ, the things above seek ye, where the Christ is, on the right hand of God seated,

2 the things above mind ye, not the things upon the earth,

3 for ye did die, and your life hath been hid with the Christ in God;

4 when the Christ--our life--may be manifested, then also we with him shall be manifested in glory.

5 Put to death, then, your members that [are] upon the earth--whoredom, uncleanness, passion, evil desire, and the covetousness, which is idolatry--

6 because of which things cometh the anger of God upon the sons of the disobedience,

7 in which also ye--ye did walk once, when ye lived in them;

8 but now put off, even ye, the whole--anger, wrath, malice, evil-speaking, filthy talking--out of your mouth.

9 Lie not one to another, having put off the old man with his practices,

10 and having put on the new, which is renewed in regard to knowledge, after the image of Him who did create him;

11 where there is not Greek and Jew, circumcision and uncircumcision, foreigner, Scythian, servant, freeman--but the all and in all--Christ.

12 Put on, therefore, as choice ones of God, holy and beloved, bowels of mercies, kindness, humble-mindedness, meekness, long-suffering,

13 forbearing one another, and forgiving each other, if any one with any one may have a quarrel, as also the Christ did forgive you--so also ye;

14 and above all these things, [have] love, which is a bond of the perfection,

15 and let the peace of God rule in your hearts, to which also ye were called in one body, and become thankful.

16 Let the word of Christ dwell in you richly, in all wisdom, teaching and admonishing each other, in psalms, and hymns, and spiritual songs, in grace singing in your hearts to the Lord;

17 and all, whatever ye may do in word or in work, [do] all things in the name of the Lord Jesus--giving thanks to the God and Father, through him.

18 The wives! be subject to your own husbands, as is fit in the Lord;

19 the husbands! love your wives, and be not bitter with them;

20 the children! obey the parents in all things, for this is well-pleasing to the Lord;

21 the fathers! vex not your children, lest they be discouraged.

22 The servants! obey in all things those who are masters according to the flesh, not in eye-service as men-pleasers, but in simplicity of heart, fearing God;

23 and all, whatever ye may do--out of soul work--as to the Lord, and not to men,

24 having known that from the Lord ye shall receive the recompense of the inheritance--for the Lord Christ ye serve;

25 and he who is doing unrighteously shall receive what he did unrighteously, and there is no acceptance of persons.

Colossians 4

1 The masters! that which is righteous and equal to the servants give ye, having known that ye also have a Master in the heavens.

2 In the prayer continue ye, watching in it in thanksgiving;

3 praying at the same time also for us, that God may open to us a door for the word, to speak the secret of the Christ, because of which also I have been bound,

4 that I may manifest it, as it behoveth me to speak;

5 in wisdom walk ye toward those without, the time forestalling;

6 your word always in grace--with salt being seasoned--to know how it behoveth you to answer each one.

7 All the things concerning me make known to you shall Tychicus--the beloved brother, and faithful ministrant, and fellow-servant in the Lord--

8 whom I did send unto you for this very thing, that he might know the things concerning you, and might comfort your hearts,

9 with Onesimus the faithful and beloved brother, who is of you; all things to you shall they make known that [are] here.

10 Salute you doth Aristarchus, my fellow-captive, and Marcus, the nephew of Barnabas, (concerning whom ye did receive commands--if he may come unto you receive him,)

11 and Jesus who is called Justus, who are of the circumcision: these only [are] fellow-workers for the reign of God who did become a comfort to me.

12 Salute you doth Epaphras, who [is] of you, a servant of Christ, always striving for you in the prayers, that ye may stand perfect and made full in all the will of God,

13 for I do testify to him, that he hath much zeal for you, and those in Laodicea, and those in Hierapolis.

14 Salute you doth Lukas, the beloved physician, and Demas;

15 salute ye those in Laodicea--brethren, and Nymphas, and the assembly in his house;

16 and when the epistle may be read with you, cause that also in the assembly of the Laodiceans it may be read, and the [epistle] from Laodicea that ye also may read;

17 and say to Archippus, `See to the ministration that thou didst receive in the Lord, that thou mayest fulfil it.'

18 The salutation by the hand of me, Paul; remember my bonds; the grace [is] with you. Amen.

2 Timothy 4

1 I do fully testify, then, before God, and the Lord Jesus Christ, who is about to judge living and dead at his manifestation and his reign--

2 preach the word; be earnest in season, out of season, convict, rebuke, exhort, in all long-suffering and teaching,

3 for there shall be a season when the sound teaching they will not suffer, but according to their own desires to themselves they shall heap up teachers--itching in the hearing,

4 and indeed, from the truth the hearing they shall turn away, and to the fables they shall be turned aside.

5 And thou--watch in all things; suffer evil; do the work of one proclaiming good news; of thy ministration make full assurance,

6 for I am already being poured out, and the time of my release hath arrived;

7 the good strife I have striven, the course I have finished, the faith I have kept,

8 henceforth there is laid up for me the crown of the righteousness that the Lord--the Righteous Judge--shall give to me in that day, and not only to me, but also to all those loving his manifestation.

9 Be diligent to come unto me quickly,

10 for Demas forsook me, having loved the present age, and went on to Thessalonica, Crescens to Galatia, Titus to Dalmatia,

11 Lukas only is with me; Markus having taken, bring with thyself, for he is profitable to me for ministration;

12 and Tychicus I sent to Ephesus;

13 the cloak that I left in Troas with Carpus, coming, bring thou and the books-- especially the parchments.

14 Alexander the coppersmith did me much evil; may the Lord repay to him according to his works,

15 of whom also do thou beware, for greatly hath he stood against our words;

16 in my first defence no one stood with me, but all forsook me, (may it not be reckoned to them!)

17 and the Lord stood by me, and did strengthen me, that through me the preaching might be fully assured, and all the nations might hear, and I was freed out of the mouth of a lion,

18 and the Lord shall free me from every evil work, and shall save [me] --to his heavenly kingdom; to whom [is] the glory to the ages of the ages! Amen.

19 Salute Prisca and Aquilas, and Onesiphorus' household;

20 Erastus did remain in Corinth, and Trophimus I left in Miletus infirm;

21 be diligent to come before winter. Salute thee doth Eubulus, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren.

22 The Lord Jesus Christ [is] with thy spirit; the grace [is] with you! Amen.

Philemon 1

1 Paul, a prisoner of Christ Jesus, and Timotheus the brother, to Philemon our beloved and fellow-worker,

2 and Apphia the beloved, and Archippus our fellow-soldier, and the assembly in thy house:

3 Grace to you, and peace, from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ!

4 I give thanks to my God, always making mention of thee in my prayers,

5 hearing of thy love and faith that thou hast unto the Lord Jesus and toward all the saints,

6 that the fellowship of thy faith may become working in the full knowledge of every good thing that [is] in you toward Christ Jesus;

7 for we have much joy and comfort in thy love, because the bowels of the saints have been refreshed through thee, brother.

8 Wherefore, having in Christ much boldness to command thee that which is fit--

9 because of the love I rather entreat, being such an one as Paul the aged, and now also a prisoner of Jesus Christ;

10 I entreat thee concerning my child--whom I did beget in my bonds--Onesimus,

11 who once was to thee unprofitable, and now is profitable to me and to thee,

12 whom I did send again, and thou him (that is, my own bowels) receive,

13 whom I did wish to retain to myself, that in thy behalf he might minister to me in the bonds of the good news,

14 and apart from thy mind I willed to do nothing, that as of necessity thy good deed may not be, but of willingness,

15 for perhaps because of this he did depart for an hour, that age-duringly thou mayest have him,

16 no more as a servant, but above a servant--a brother beloved, especially to me, and how much more to thee, both in the flesh and in the Lord!

17 If, then, with me thou hast fellowship, receive him as me,

18 and if he did hurt to thee, or doth owe anything, this to me be reckoning;

19 I, Paul did write with my hand, I--I will repay; that I may not say that also thyself, besides, to me thou dost owe.

20 Yes, brother, may I have profit of thee in the Lord; refresh my bowels in the Lord;

21 having been confident in thy obedience I did write to thee, having known that also above what I may say thou wilt do;

22 and at the same time also prepare for me a lodging, for I hope that through your prayers I shall be granted to you.

23 Salute thee doth Epaphras, (my fellow-captive in Christ Jesus,)

24 Markus, Aristarchus, Demas, Lukas, my fellow-workmen!

25 The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ [is] with your spirit! Amen.

Hebrews 13

1 Let brotherly love remain;

2 of the hospitality be not forgetful, for through this unawares certain did entertain messengers;

3 be mindful of those in bonds, as having been bound with them, of those maltreated, as also yourselves being in the body;

4 honourable [is] the marriage in all, and the bed undefiled, and whoremongers and adulterers God shall judge.

5 Without covetousness the behaviour, being content with the things present, for He hath said, `No, I will not leave, no, nor forsake thee,'

6 so that we do boldly say, `The Lord [is] to me a helper, and I will not fear what man shall do to me.'

7 Be mindful of those leading you, who did speak to you the word of God, whose faith--considering the issue of the behaviour--be imitating,

8 Jesus Christ yesterday and to-day the same, and to the ages;

9 with teachings manifold and strange be not carried about, for [it is] good that by grace the heart be confirmed, not with meats, in which they who were occupied were not profited;

10 we have an altar, of which to eat they have no authority who the tabernacle are serving,

11 for of those beasts whose blood is brought for sin into the holy places through the chief priest--of these the bodies are burned without the camp.

12 Wherefore, also Jesus--that he might sanctify through [his] own blood the people-- without the gate did suffer;

13 now, then, may we go forth unto him without the camp, his reproach bearing;

14 for we have not here an abiding city, but the coming one we seek;

15 through him, then, we may offer up a sacrifice of praise always to God, that is, the fruit of lips, giving thanks to His name;

16 and of doing good, and of fellowship, be not forgetful, for with such sacrifices God is well-pleased.

17 Be obedient to those leading you, and be subject, for these do watch for your souls, as about to give account, that with joy they may do this, and not sighing, for this [is] unprofitable to you.

18 Pray for us, for we trust that we have a good conscience, in all things willing to behave well,

19 and more abundantly do I call upon [you] to do this, that more quickly I may be restored to you.

20 And the God of the peace, who did bring up out of the dead the great shepherd of the sheep--in the blood of an age-during covenant--our Lord Jesus,

21 make you perfect in every good work to do His will, doing in you that which is well-pleasing before Him, through Jesus Christ, to whom [is] the glory--to the ages of the ages! Amen.

22 And I entreat you, brethren, suffer the word of the exhortation, for also through few words I have written to you.

23 Know ye that the brother Timotheus is released, with whom, if he may come more shortly, I will see you.

24 Salute all those leading you, and all the saints; salute you doth those from Italy:

25 the grace [is] with you all! Amen.

James 2

1 My brethren, hold not, in respect of persons, the faith of the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ,

2 for if there may come into your synagogue a man with gold ring, in gay raiment, and there may come in also a poor man in vile raiment,

3 and ye may look upon him bearing the gay raiment, and may say to him, `Thou--sit thou here well,' and to the poor man may say, `Thou--stand thou there, or, Sit thou here under my footstool,' --

4 ye did not judge fully in yourselves, and did become ill-reasoning judges.

5 Hearken, my brethren beloved, did not God choose the poor of this world, rich in faith, and heirs of the reign that He promised to those loving Him?

6 and ye did dishonour the poor one; do not the rich oppress you and themselves draw you to judgment-seats;

7 do they not themselves speak evil of the good name that was called upon you?

8 If, indeed, royal law ye complete, according to the Writing, `Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself,' --ye do well;

9 and if ye accept persons, sin ye do work, being convicted by the law as transgressors;

10 for whoever the whole law shall keep, and shall stumble in one [point], he hath become guilty of all;

11 for He who is saying, `Thou mayest not commit adultery,' said also, `Thou mayest do no murder;' and if thou shalt not commit adultery, and shalt commit murder, thou hast become a transgressor of law;

12 so speak ye and so do, as about by a law of liberty to be judged,

13 for the judgment without kindness [is] to him not having done kindness, and exult doth kindness over judgment.

14 What [is] the profit, my brethren, if faith, any one may speak of having, and works he may not have? is that faith able to save him?

15 and if a brother or sister may be naked, and may be destitute of the daily food,

16 and any one of you may say to them, `Depart ye in peace, be warmed, and be filled,' and may not give to them the things needful for the body, what [is] the profit?

17 so also the faith, if it may not have works, is dead by itself.

18 But say may some one, Thou hast faith, and I have works, shew me thy faith out of thy works, and I will shew thee out of my works my faith:

19 thou--thou dost believe that God is one; thou dost well, and the demons believe, and they shudder!

20 And dost thou wish to know, O vain man, that the faith apart from the works is dead?

21 Abraham our father--was not he declared righteous out of works, having brought up Isaac his son upon the altar?

22 dost thou see that the faith was working with his works, and out of the works the faith was perfected?

23 and fulfilled was the Writing that is saying, `And Abraham did believe God, and it was reckoned to him--to righteousness;' and, `Friend of God' he was called.

24 Ye see, then, that out of works is man declared righteous, and not out of faith only;

25 and in like manner also Rahab the harlot--was she not out of works declared righteous, having received the messengers, and by another way having sent forth?

26 for as the body apart from the spirit is dead, so also the faith apart from the works is dead.

James 3

1 Many teachers become not, my brethren, having known that greater judgment we shall receive,

2 for we all make many stumbles; if any one in word doth not stumble, this one [is] a perfect man, able to bridle also the whole body;

3 lo, the bits we put into the mouths of the horses for their obeying us, and their whole body we turn about;

4 lo, also the ships, being so great, and by fierce winds being driven, are led about by a very small helm, whithersoever the impulse of the helmsman doth counsel,

5 so also the tongue is a little member, and doth boast greatly; lo, a little fire how much wood it doth kindle!

6 and the tongue [is] a fire, the world of the unrighteousness, so the tongue is set in our members, which is spotting our whole body, and is setting on fire the course of nature, and is set on fire by the gehenna.

7 For every nature, both of beasts and of fowls, both of creeping things and things of the sea, is subdued, and hath been subdued, by the human nature,

8 and the tongue no one of men is able to subdue, [it is] an unruly evil, full of deadly poison,

9 with it we do bless the God and Father, and with it we do curse the men made according to the similitude of God;

10 out of the same mouth doth come forth blessing and cursing; it doth not need, my brethren, these things so to happen;

11 doth the fountain out of the same opening pour forth the sweet and the bitter?

12 is a fig-tree able, my brethren, olives to make? or a vine figs? so no fountain salt and sweet water [is able] to make.

13 Who [is] wise and intelligent among you? let him shew out of the good behaviour his works in meekness of wisdom,

14 and if bitter zeal ye have, and rivalry in your heart, glory not, nor lie against the truth;

15 this wisdom is not descending from above, but earthly, physical, demon-like,

16 for where zeal and rivalry [are], there is insurrection and every evil matter;

17 and the wisdom from above, first, indeed, is pure, then peaceable, gentle, easily entreated, full of kindness and good fruits, uncontentious, and unhypocritical: --

18 and the fruit of the righteousness in peace is sown to those making peace.

James 4

1 Whence [are] wars and fightings among you? not thence--out of your passions, that are as soldiers in your members?

2 ye desire, and ye have not; ye murder, and are zealous, and are not able to attain; ye fight and war, and ye have not, because of your not asking;

3 ye ask, and ye receive not, because evilly ye ask, that in your pleasures ye may spend [it].

4 Adulterers and adulteresses! have ye not known that friendship of the world is enmity with God? whoever, then, may counsel to be a friend of the world, an enemy of God he is set.

5 Do ye think that emptily the Writing saith, `To envy earnestly desireth the spirit that did dwell in us,'

6 and greater grace he doth give, wherefore he saith, `God against proud ones doth set Himself up, and to lowly ones He doth give grace?'

7 be subject, then, to God; stand up against the devil, and he will flee from you;

8 draw nigh to God, and He will draw nigh to you; cleanse hands, ye sinners! and purify hearts, ye two-souled!

9 be exceeding afflicted, and mourn, and weep, let your laughter to mourning be turned, and the joy to heaviness;

10 be made low before the Lord, and He shall exalt you.

11 Speak not one against another, brethren; he who is speaking against a brother, and is judging his brother, doth speak against law, and doth judge law, and if law thou dost judge, thou art not a doer of law but a judge;

12 one is the lawgiver, who is able to save and to destroy; thou--who art thou that dost judge the other?

13 Go, now, ye who are saying, `To-day and to-morrow we will go on to such a city, and will pass there one year, and traffic, and make gain;'

14 who do not know the thing of the morrow; for what is your life? for it is a vapour that is appearing for a little, and then is vanishing;

15 instead of your saying, `If the Lord may will, we shall live, and do this or that;'

16 and now ye glory in your pride; all such glorying is evil;

17 to him, then, knowing to do good, and not doing, sin it is to him.

James 5

1 Go, now, ye rich! weep, howling over your miseries that are coming upon [you];

2 your riches have rotted, and your garments have become moth-eaten;

3 your gold and silver have rotted, and the rust of them for a testimony shall be to you, and shall eat your flesh as fire. Ye made treasure in the last days!

4 lo, the reward of the workmen, of those who in-gathered your fields, which hath been fraudulently kept back by you--doth cry out, and the exclamations of those who did reap into the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth have entered;

5 ye did live in luxury upon the earth, and were wanton; ye did nourish your hearts, as in a day of slaughter;

6 ye did condemn--ye did murder the righteous one, he doth not resist you.

7 Be patient, then, brethren, till the presence of the Lord; lo, the husbandman doth expect the precious fruit of the earth, being patient for it, till he may receive rain--early and latter;

8 be patient, ye also; establish your hearts, because the presence of the Lord hath drawn nigh;

9 murmur not against one another, brethren, that ye may not be condemned; lo, the Judge before the door hath stood.

10 An example take ye of the suffering of evil, my brethren, and of the patience, the prophets who did speak in the name of the Lord;

11 lo, we call happy those who are enduring; the endurance of Job ye heard of, and the end of the Lord ye have seen, that very compassionate is the Lord, and pitying.

12 And before all things, my brethren, do not swear, neither by the heaven, neither by the earth, neither by any other oath, and let your Yes be Yes, and the No, No; that under judgment ye may not fall.

13 Doth any one suffer evil among you? let him pray; is any of good cheer? let him sing psalms;

14 is any infirm among you? let him call for the elders of the assembly, and let them pray over him, having anointed him with oil, in the name of the Lord,

15 and the prayer of the faith shall save the distressed one, and the Lord shall raise him up, and if sins he may have committed, they shall be forgiven to him.

16 Be confessing to one another the trespasses, and be praying for one another, that ye may be healed; very strong is a working supplication of a righteous man;

17 Elijah was a man like affected as we, and with prayer he did pray--not to rain, and it did not rain upon the land three years and six months;

18 and again he did pray, and the heaven did give rain, and the land did bring forth her fruit.

19 Brethren, if any among you may go astray from the truth, and any one may turn him back,

20 let him know that he who did turn back a sinner from the straying of his way shall save a soul from death, and shall cover a multitude of sins.

1 Peter 5

1 Elders who [are] among you, I exhort, who [am] a fellow-elder, and a witness of the sufferings of the Christ, and of the glory about to be revealed a partaker,

2 feed the flock of God that [is] among you, overseeing not constrainedly, but willingly, neither for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind,

3 neither as exercising lordship over the heritages, but patterns becoming of the flock,

4 and at the manifestation of the chief Shepherd, ye shall receive the unfading crown of glory.

5 In like manner, ye younger, be subject to elders, and all to one another subjecting yourselves; with humble-mindedness clothe yourselves, because God the proud doth resist, but to the humble He doth give grace;

6 be humbled, then, under the powerful hand of God, that you He may exalt in good time,

7 all your care having cast upon Him, because He careth for you.

8 Be sober, vigilant, because your opponent the devil, as a roaring lion, doth walk about, seeking whom he may swallow up,

9 whom resist, stedfast in the faith, having known the same sufferings to your brotherhood in the world to be accomplished.

10 And the God of all grace, who did call you to His age-during glory in Christ Jesus, having suffered a little, Himself make you perfect, establish, strengthen, settle [you];

11 to Him [is] the glory, and the power--to the ages and the ages! Amen.

12 Through Silvanus, to you the faithful brother, as I reckon, through few [words] I did write, exhorting and testifying this to be the true grace of God in which ye have stood.

13 Salute you doth the [assembly] in Babylon jointly elected, and Markus my son.

14 Salute ye one another in a kiss of love; peace to you all who [are] in Christ Jesus! Amen.

1 John 2

1 My little children, these things I write to you, that ye may not sin: and if any one may sin, an advocate we have with the Father, Jesus Christ, a righteous one,

2 and he--he is a propitiation for our sins, and not for ours only, but also for the whole world,

3 and in this we know that we have known him, if his commands we may keep;

4 he who is saying, `I have known him,' and his command is not keeping, a liar he is, and in him the truth is not;

5 and whoever may keep his word, truly in him the love of God hath been perfected; in this we know that in him we are.

6 He who is saying in him he doth remain, ought according as he walked also himself so to walk.

7 Brethren, a new command I write not to you, but an old command, that ye had from the beginning--the old command is the word that ye heard from the beginning;

8 again, a new command I write to you, which thing is true in him and in you, because the darkness doth pass away, and the true light doth now shine;

9 he who is saying, in the light he is, and his brother is hating, in the darkness he is till now;

10 he who is loving his brother, in the light he doth remain, and a stumbling-block in him there is not;

11 and he who is hating his brother, in the darkness he is, and in the darkness he doth walk, and he hath not known whither he doth go, because the darkness did blind his eyes.

12 I write to you, little children, because the sins have been forgiven you through his name;

13 I write to you, fathers, because ye have known him who [is] from the beginning; I write to you, young men, because ye have overcome the evil. I write to you, little youths, because ye have known the Father:

14 I did write to you, fathers, because ye have known him who [is] from the beginning; I did write to you, young men, because ye are strong, and the word of God in you doth remain, and ye have overcome the evil.

15 Love not ye the world, nor the things in the world; if any one doth love the world, the love of the Father is not in him,

16 because all that [is] in the world--the desire of the flesh, and the desire of the eyes, and the ostentation of the life--is not of the Father, but of the world,

17 and the world doth pass away, and the desire of it, and he who is doing the will of God, he doth remain--to the age.

18 Little youths, it is the last hour; and even as ye heard that the antichrist doth come, even now antichrists have become many--whence we know that it is the last hour;

19 out of us they went forth, but they were not of us, for if they had been of us, they would have remained with us; but--that they might be manifested that they are not all of us.

20 And ye have an anointing from the Holy One, and have known all things;

21 I did not write to you because ye have not known the truth, but because ye have known it, and because no lie is of the truth.

22 Who is the liar, except he who is denying that Jesus is the Christ? this one is the antichrist who is denying the Father and the Son;

23 every one who is denying the Son, neither hath he the Father, [he who is confessing the Son hath the Father also.]

24 Ye, then, that which ye heard from the beginning, in you let it remain; if in you may remain that which from the beginning ye did hear, ye also in the Son and in the Father shall remain,

25 and this is the promise that He did promise us--the life the age-during.

26 These things I did write to you concerning those leading you astray;

27 and you, the anointing that ye did receive from him, in you it doth remain, and ye have no need that any one may teach you, but as the same anointing doth teach you concerning all, and is true, and is not a lie, and even as was taught you, yeshall remain in him.

28 And now, little children, remain in him, that when he may be manifested, we may have boldness, and may not be ashamed before him, in his presence;

29 if ye know that he is righteous, know ye that every one doing the righteousness, of him hath been begotten.

1 John 3

1 See ye what love the Father hath given to us, that children of God we may be called; because of this the world doth not know us, because it did not know Him;

2 beloved, now, children of God are we, and it was not yet manifested what we shall be, and we have known that if he may be manifested, like him we shall be, because we shall see him as he is;

3 and every one who is having this hope on him, doth purify himself, even as he is pure.

4 Every one who is doing the sin, the lawlessness also he doth do, and the sin is the lawlessness,

5 and ye have known that he was manifested that our sins he may take away, and sin is not in him;

6 every one who is remaining in him doth not sin; every one who is sinning, hath not seen him, nor known him.

7 Little children, let no one lead you astray; he who is doing the righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous,

8 he who is doing the sin, of the devil he is, because from the beginning the devil doth sin; for this was the Son of God manifested, that he may break up the works of the devil;

9 every one who hath been begotten of God, sin he doth not, because his seed in him doth remain, and he is not able to sin, because of God he hath been begotten.

10 In this manifest are the children of God, and the children of the devil; every one who is not doing righteousness, is not of God, and he who is not loving his brother,

11 because this is the message that ye did hear from the beginning, that we may love one another,

12 not as Cain--of the evil one he was, and he did slay his brother, and wherefore did he slay him? because his works were evil, and those of his brother righteous.

13 Do not wonder, my brethren, if the world doth hate you;

14 we--we have known that we have passed out of the death to the life, because we love the brethren; he who is not loving the brother doth remain in the death.

15 Every one who is hating his brother--a man-killer he is, and ye have known that no man-killer hath life age-during in him remaining,

16 in this we have known the love, because he for us his life did lay down, and we ought for the brethren the lives to lay down;

17 and whoever may have the goods of the world, and may view his brother having need, and may shut up his bowels from him--how doth the love of God remain in him?

18 My little children, may we not love in word nor in tongue, but in word and in truth!

19 and in this we know that of the truth we are, and before Him we shall assure our hearts,

20 because if our heart may condemn--because greater is God than our heart, and He doth know all things.

21 Beloved, if our heart may not condemn us, we have boldness toward God,

22 and whatever we may ask, we receive from Him, because His commands we keep, and the things pleasing before Him we do,

23 and this is His command, that we may believe in the name of His Son Jesus Christ, and may love one another, even as He did give command to us,

24 and he who is keeping His commands, in Him he doth remain, and He in him; and in this we know that He doth remain in us, from the Spirit that He gave us.

1 John 4

1 Beloved, every spirit believe not, but prove the spirits, if of God they are, because many false prophets have gone forth to the world;

2 in this know ye the Spirit of God; every spirit that doth confess Jesus Christ in the flesh having come, of God it is,

3 and every spirit that doth not confess Jesus Christ in the flesh having come, of God it is not; and this is that of the antichrist, which ye heard that it doth come, and now in the world it is already.

4 Ye--of God ye are, little children, and ye have overcome them; because greater is He who [is] in you, than he who is in the world.

5 They--of the world they are; because of this from the world they speak, and the world doth hear them;

6 we--of God we are; he who is knowing God doth hear us; he who is not of God, doth not hear us; from this we know the spirit of the truth, and the spirit of the error.

7 Beloved, may we love one another, because the love is of God, and every one who is loving, of God he hath been begotten, and doth know God;

8 he who is not loving did not know God, because God is love.

9 In this was manifested the love of God in us, because His Son--the only begotten--hath God sent to the world, that we may live through him;

10 in this is the love, not that we loved God, but that He did love us, and did send His Son a propitiation for our sins.

11 Beloved, if thus did God love us, we also ought one another to love;

12 God no one hath ever seen; if we may love one another, God in us doth remain, and His love is having been perfected in us;

13 in this we know that in Him we do remain, and He in us, because of His Spirit He hath given us.

14 And we--we have seen and do testify, that the Father hath sent the Son--Saviour of the world;

15 whoever may confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God in him doth remain, and he in God;

16 and we--we have known and believed the love, that God hath in us; God is love, and he who is remaining in the love, in God he doth remain, and God in him.

17 In this made perfect hath been the love with us, that boldness we may have in the day of the judgment, because even as He is, we--we also are in this world;

18 fear is not in the love, but the perfect love doth cast out the fear, because the fear hath punishment, and he who is fearing hath not been made perfect in the love;

19 we--we love him, because He--He first loved us;

20 if any one may say--`I love God,' and his brother he may hate, a liar he is; for he who is not loving his brother whom he hath seen, God--whom he hath not seen--how is he able to love?

21 and this [is] the command we have from Him, that he who is loving God, may also love his brother.

1 John 5

1 Every one who is believing that Jesus is the Christ, of God he hath been begotten, and every one who is loving Him who did beget, doth love also him who is begotten of Him:

2 in this we know that we love the children of God, when we may love God, and His commands may keep;

3 for this is the love of God, that His commands we may keep, and His commands are not burdensome;

4 because every one who is begotten of God doth overcome the world, and this is the victory that did overcome the world--our faith;

5 who is he who is overcoming the world, if not he who is believing that Jesus is the Son of God?

6 This one is he who did come through water and blood--Jesus the Christ, not in the water only, but in the water and the blood; and the Spirit it is that is testifying, because the Spirit is the truth,

7 because three are who are testifying [in the heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Spirit, and these--the three--are one;

8 and three are who are testifying in the earth], the Spirit, and the water, and the blood, and the three are into the one.

9 If the testimony of men we receive, the testimony of God is greater, because this is the testimony of God that He hath testified concerning His Son.

10 He who is believing in the Son of God, hath the testimony in himself; he who is not believing God, a liar hath made Him, because he hath not believed in the testimony that God hath testified concerning His Son;

11 and this is the testimony, that life age-during did God give to us, and this--the life--is in His Son;

12 he who is having the Son, hath the life; he who is not having the Son of God--the life he hath not.

13 These things I did write to you who are believing in the name of the Son of God, that ye may know that life ye have age-during, and that ye may believe in the name of the Son of God.

14 And this is the boldness that we have toward Him, that if anything we may ask according to his will, He doth hear us,

15 and if we have known that He doth hear us, whatever we may ask, we have known that we have the requests that we have requested from Him.

16 If any one may see his brother sinning a sin not unto death, he shall ask, and He shall give to him life to those sinning not unto death; there is sin to death, not concerning it do I speak that he may beseech;

17 all unrighteousness is sin, and there is sin not unto death.

18 We have known that every one who hath been begotten of God doth not sin, but he who was begotten of God doth keep himself, and the evil one doth not touch him;

19 we have known that of God we are, and the whole world in the evil doth lie;

20 and we have known that the Son of God is come, and hath given us a mind, that we may know Him who is true, and we are in Him who is true, in His Son Jesus Christ; this one is the true God and the life age-during!

21 Little children, guard yourselves from the idols! Amen.

3 John 1

1 The Elder to Gaius the beloved, whom I love in truth!

2 beloved, concerning all things I desire thee to prosper, and to be in health, even as thy soul doth prosper,

3 for I rejoiced exceedingly, brethren coming and testifying of the truth in thee, even as thou in truth dost walk;

4 greater than these things I have no joy, that I may hear of my children in truth walking.

5 Beloved, faithfully dost thou do whatever thou mayest work to the brethren and to the strangers,

6 who did testify of thy love before an assembly, whom thou wilt do well, having sent forward worthily of God,

7 because for [His] name they went forth, nothing receiving from the nations;

8 we, then, ought to receive such, that fellow-workers we may become to the truth.

9 I did write to the assembly, but he who is loving the first place among them-- Diotrephes--doth not receive us;

10 because of this, if I may come, I will cause him to remember his works that he doth, with evil words prating against us; and not content with these, neither doth he himself receive the brethren, and those intending he doth forbid, and out of the assembly he doth cast.

11 Beloved, be not thou following that which is evil, but that which is good; he who is doing good, of God he is, and he who is doing evil hath not seen God;

12 to Demetrius testimony hath been given by all, and by the truth itself, and we also-- we do testify, and ye have known that our testimony is true.

13 Many things I had to write, but I do not wish through ink and pen to write to thee,

14 and I hope straightway to see thee, and mouth to mouth we shall speak. Peace to thee! salute thee do the friends; be saluting the friends by name.

Revelation 1

1 A revelation of Jesus Christ, that God gave to him, to shew to his servants what things it behoveth to come to pass quickly; and he did signify [it], having sent through his messenger to his servant John,

2 who did testify the word of God, and the testimony of Jesus Christ, as many things also as he did see.

3 Happy is he who is reading, and those hearing, the words of the prophecy, and keeping the things written in it--for the time is nigh!

4 John to the seven assemblies that [are] in Asia: Grace to you, and peace, from Him who is, and who was, and who is coming, and from the Seven Spirits that are before His throne,

5 and from Jesus Christ, the faithful witness, the first-born out of the dead, and the ruler of the kings of the earth; to him who did love us, and did bathe us from our sins in his blood,

6 and did make us kings and priests to his God and Father, to him [is] the glory and the power to the ages of the ages! Amen.

7 Lo, he doth come with the clouds, and see him shall every eye, even those who did pierce him, and wail because of him shall all the tribes of the land. Yes! Amen!

8 `I am the Alpha and the Omega, beginning and end, saith the Lord, who is, and who was, and who is coming--the Almighty.'

9 I, John, who also [am] your brother, and fellow-partner in the tribulation, and in the reign and endurance, of Jesus Christ, was in the isle that is called Patmos, because of the word of God, and because of the testimony of Jesus Christ;

10 I was in the Spirit on the Lord's-day, and I heard behind me a great voice, as of a trumpet, saying,

11 `I am the Alpha and the Omega, the First and the Last;' and, `What thou dost see, write in a scroll, and send to the seven assemblies that [are] in Asia; to Ephesus, and to Smyrna, and to Pergamos, and to Thyatira, and to Sardis, and to Philadelphia, and to Laodicea.'

12 And I did turn to see the voice that did speak with me, and having turned, I saw seven golden lamp-stands,

13 and in the midst of the seven lamp-stands, [one] like to a son of man, clothed to the foot, and girt round at the breast with a golden girdle,

14 and his head and hairs white, as if white wool--as snow, and his eyes as a flame of fire;

15 and his feet like to fine brass, as in a furnace having been fired, and his voice as a sound of many waters,

16 and having in his right hand seven stars, and out of his mouth a sharp two-edged sword is proceeding, and his countenance [is] as the sun shining in its might.

17 And when I saw him, I did fall at his feet as dead, and he placed his right hand upon me, saying to me, `Be not afraid; I am the First and the Last,

18 and he who is living, and I did become dead, and, lo, I am living to the ages of the ages. Amen! and I have the keys of the hades and of the death.

19 `Write the things that thou hast seen, and the things that are, and the things that are about to come after these things;

20 the secret of the seven stars that thou hast seen upon my right hand, and the seven golden lamp-stands: the seven stars are messengers of the seven assemblies, and the seven lampstands that thou hast seen are seven assemblies.

Revelation 2

1 `To the messenger of the Ephesian assembly write: These things saith he who is holding the seven stars in his right hand, who is walking in the midst of the seven lamp-stands--the golden:

2 I have known thy works, and thy labour, and thy endurance, and that thou art not able to bear evil ones, and that thou hast tried those saying themselves to be apostles and are not, and hast found them liars,

3 and thou didst bear, and hast endurance, and because of my name hast toiled, and hast not been weary.

4 `But I have against thee: That thy first love thou didst leave!

5 remember, then, whence thou hast fallen, and reform, and the first works do; and if not, I come to thee quickly, and will remove thy lamp-stand from its place--if thou mayest not reform;

6 but this thou hast, that thou dost hate the works of the Nicolaitans, that I also hate.

7 He who is having an ear--let him hear what the Spirit saith to the assemblies: To him who is overcoming--I will give to him to eat of the tree of life that is in the midst of the paradise of God.

8 `And to the messenger of the assembly of the Smyrneans write: These things saith the First and the Last, who did become dead and did live;

9 I have known thy works, and tribulation, and poverty--yet thou art rich--and the evil-speaking of those saying themselves to be Jews, and are not, but [are] a synagogue of the Adversary.

10 `Be not afraid of the things that thou art about to suffer; lo, the devil is about to cast of you to prison, that ye may be tried, and ye shall have tribulation ten days; become thou faithful unto death, and I will give to thee the crown of the life.

11 He who is having an ear--let him hear what the Spirit saith to the assemblies: He who is overcoming may not be injured of the second death.

12 `And to the messenger of the assembly in Pergamos write: These things saith he who is having the sharp two-edged sword:

13 I have known thy works, and where thou dost dwell--where the throne of the Adversary [is] --and thou dost hold fast my name, and thou didst not deny my faith, even in the days in which Antipas [was] my faithful witness, who was put to death beside you, where the Adversary doth dwell.

14 `But I have against thee a few things: That thou hast there those holding the teaching of Balaam, who did teach Balak to cast a stumbling-block before the sons of Israel, to eat idol-sacrifices, and to commit whoredom;

15 so hast thou, even thou, those holding the teaching of the Nicolaitans--which thing I hate.

16 `Reform! and if not, I come to thee quickly, and will fight against them with the sword of my mouth.

17 He who is having an ear--let him hear what the Spirit saith to the assemblies: To him who is overcoming, I will give to him to eat from the hidden manna, and will give to him a white stone, and upon the stone a new name written, that no one knew except him who is receiving [it].

18 `And to the messenger of the assembly of Thyatira write: These things saith the Son of God, who is having his eyes as a flame of fire, and his feet like to fine brass;

19 I have known thy works, and love, and ministration, and faith, and thy endurance, and thy works--and the last [are] more than the first.

20 `But I have against thee a few things: That thou dost suffer the woman Jezebel, who is calling herself a prophetess, to teach, and to lead astray, my servants to commit whoredom, and idol-sacrifices to eat;

21 and I did give to her a time that she might reform from her whoredom, and she did not reform;

22 lo, I will cast her into a couch, and those committing adultery with her into great tribulation--if they may not repent of their works,

23 and her children I will kill in death, and know shall all the assemblies that I am he who is searching reins and hearts; and I will give to you--to each--according to your works.

24 `And to you I say, and to the rest who are in Thyatira, as many as have not this teaching, and who did not know the depths of the Adversary, as they say; I will not put upon you other burden;

25 but that which ye have--hold ye, till I may come;

26 and he who is overcoming, and who is keeping unto the end my works, I will give to him authority over the nations,

27 and he shall rule them with a rod of iron--as the vessels of the potter they shall be broken--as I also have received from my Father;

28 and I will give to him the morning star.

29 He who is having an ear--let him hear what the Spirit saith to the assemblies.

Revelation 3

1 And to the messenger of the assembly in Sardis write: These things saith he who is having the Seven Spirits of God, and the seven stars: I have known thy works, and that thou hast the name that thou dost live, and thou art dead;

2 become watching, and strengthen the rest of the things that are about to die, for I have not found thy works fulfilled before God.

3 `Remember, then, how thou hast received, and heard, and be keeping, and reform: if, then, thou mayest not watch, I will come upon thee as a thief, and thou mayest not know what hour I will come upon thee.

4 Thou hast a few names even in Sardis who did not defile their garments, and they shall walk with me in white, because they are worthy.

5 He who is overcoming--this one--shall be arrayed in white garments, and I will not blot out his name from the scroll of the life, and I will confess his name before my Father, and before His messengers.

6 He who is having an ear--let him hear what the Spirit saith to the assemblies.

7 `And to the messenger of the assembly in Philadelphia write: These things saith he who is holy, he who is true, he who is having the key of David, he who is opening and no one doth shut, and he shutteth and no one doth open!

8 I have known thy works; lo, I have set before thee a door--opened, and no one is able to shut it, because thou hast a little power, and didst keep my word, and didst not deny my name;

9 lo, I make of the synagogue of the Adversary those saying themselves to be Jews, and are not, but do lie; lo, I will make them that they may come and bow before thy feet, and may know that I loved thee.

10 `Because thou didst keep the word of my endurance, I also will keep thee from the hour of the trial that is about to come upon all the world, to try those dwelling upon the earth.

11 Lo, I come quickly, be holding fast that which thou hast, that no one may receive thy crown.

12 He who is overcoming--I will make him a pillar in the sanctuary of my God, and without he may not go any more, and I will write upon him the name of my God, and the name of the city of my God, the new Jerusalem, that doth come down out ofthe heaven from my God--also my new name.

13 He who is having an ear--let him hear what the Spirit saith to the assemblies.

14 `And to the messenger of the assembly of the Laodiceans write: These things saith the Amen, the witness--the faithful and true--the chief of the creation of God;

15 I have known thy works, that neither cold art thou nor hot; I would thou wert cold or hot.

16 So--because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I am about to vomit thee out of my mouth;

17 because thou sayest--I am rich, and have grown rich, and have need of nothing, and hast not known that thou art the wretched, and miserable, and poor, and blind, and naked,

18 I counsel thee to buy from me gold fired by fire, that thou mayest be rich, and white garments that thou mayest be arrayed, and the shame of thy nakedness may not be manifest, and with eye-salve anoint thine eyes, that thou mayest see.

19 `As many as I love, I do convict and chasten; be zealous, then, and reform;

20 lo, I have stood at the door, and I knock; if any one may hear my voice, and may open the door, I will come in unto him, and will sup with him, and he with me.

21 He who is overcoming--I will give to him to sit with me in my throne, as I also did overcome and did sit down with my Father in His throne.

22 He who is having an ear--let him hear what the Spirit saith to the assemblies.'